<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Svvethland and Poland vvarres A souldiers returne out of Sweden, and his newes from the warres: or, Sweden and Poland vp in armes. And the entertainement of English souldiers there: with the fortunes and successe of those 1200. men that lately went thither.</title>
            <author>Nixon, Anthony.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125498</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898211</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135785</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135785)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2082:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Svvethland and Poland vvarres A souldiers returne out of Sweden, and his newes from the warres: or, Sweden and Poland vp in armes. And the entertainement of English souldiers there: with the fortunes and successe of those 1200. men that lately went thither.</title>
                  <author>Nixon, Anthony.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p. : ill (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Nathaniell Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>By Anthony Nixon --STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swedish-Polish War, 1617-1629 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Poland --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sweden --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:135785:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135785:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135785:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135785:2"/>
            <p>SVVETHLAND and Poland VVarres.</p>
            <p>A Souldiers returne out of Sweden, and his Newes from the Warres: OR, <hi>Sweden and Poland vp in Armes.</hi> And the entertainement of Engliſh Souldiers there: with the fortunes and ſucceſſe of thoſe 1200. men that lately went thither.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>At London printed for <hi>Nathaniell Butter.</hi> 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:135785:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135785:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ountrymen, I haue for your ſakes drawne a Picture, both of my owne, and other Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmens miſeries: You may in halfe an hower runne ouer theſe afflictions, which I and the reſt (that ſmarted by them) were many months enduring. I know it ſhall be a pleaſure to you, to reade what wee haue ſelt; and as great a happineſſe to me (who haue publiſhed this:) if the Story of a poore Souldiers trauels, can bring you any contentment, let me finde at your handes (I intreate you) the ſelfe ſame loue which Sicke-men receiue from their friendes, when they begin to recouer; And that is a kinde viſitation and reioycing, to ſee a crazed and weake body reduced to his former ſtrength: Mine (I thanke God) is now ſo, and ſhall grow
<pb facs="tcp:135785:4"/>more and more into health, by how much the more you pittie my misfortunes: you cannot pittie them, vnleſſe you know them, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not know them vnleſſe you reade this ouer which I ſende you; and I would not willingly haue you read, vnleſſe you buy, becauſe you ſhould pay for the Warres ſomewhat as well as I: not doubting therefore of the one, becauſe I hope you deſire the other: I wiſh your owne wiſhes to you: and ſo farewell.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135785:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135785:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:135785:5"/>
            <head>A Souldiers Returne out of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and his Newes from the Warres.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Oliue Tree of Peace (vpon which groweth the happineſſe, wealth and proſperitie of euerie Kingdome) hath flouriſhed (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vp to his full height) ſo long in <hi>England,</hi> that other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Kingdomes neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by her, beholding the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, benefits and contentation which <hi>England</hi> hath gathered by taſting the fruites of Peace, haue gotten ſome braunches of that Tree, and (by our example) planted the ſame in their owne Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions. In doing of which, the French haue filled their Coffers with Treaſures, which before were ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by violence, empried by ſeditious Leagues, and waſted to nothing by the miſeries of a tedious and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine warre: the Spaniſh haue likewiſe with the ſame ſtreame ſafely returned from the Mines of both Indies, and richly vnladed their Argozies of Indian golde, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their owne ſhoares, of which golde (before Peace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited amongſt them) they were euer leaſt ſaue when they approached neareſt home, as the bringers of it from thence hither, and the looſers of it there, did in thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:135785:6"/>times (the one with ioy, the other with madnes and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row) openly teſtifie.</p>
            <p>So that theſe fires (whether of Ambition, of Zeale, or of Rage, I knowe not) which for many late yéeres haue named in the Low Countries, had not bin kindled there, I thinke the very name of Warre had bin almoſt forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and the right pronunciation of it vnknowne to theſe parts of chriſtendome. The violent heate of which Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke fires was ſo laſting, and burned ſo high, that it ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as a Beacon on the top of a hill, to call vnto their help other forren nations (who before were but lookers on) and inticed them (through the thirſt of glory, honour and fame which are gotten in the fires) to become partners and ſharers in the variable fortunes of thoſe Battelles of the Dutch and Spaniſh. Inſomuch that the Drumme being vnbraced héere, and hung vp by the walls (as hauing no vſe of ſuch thunder amongſt vs, vnleſſe it were for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,) and moſt of our men of Action and of the Sword hearing the ſound of theirs, and being drawne thither, I thinke it was then, and is now ſtil poſſible to call together 20000. of our engliſh nation into one place, and amongſt them all not to find or picke out one Souldier, when in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forren realmes (vext continually with vproares) it hath hin, and to this day is hard to call together <hi>100000.</hi> and to cull out of them any other perſon but a Souldier.</p>
            <p>The Schoole of Warre decaying, and being throwne downe in one kingdome, hath from time to time bin exec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in another. And as men who profeſſe other Arts and Sciences, will (if they loue them truely) trauell ouer the world to enrich their boſomes with the perfit knowledge of thoſe things with which their ſoules are inflamed: So the militarie Scholler (whoſe beſt learning is Practiſe,) accounteth euery Land his owne country where this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Armes is held in honor: and no loue of parents, wife, children, kinred or friends hath power to kéepe him from thoſe glorious paths of danger.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135785:6"/>
By this meanes, many Engliſhmen that were borne obſcurely, and might (otherwiſe) haue died forgotten, haue by their noble aduentures and ſeruices in forren realmes (farre hence remoted) not onely won eternall honours to their owne names, but alſo crowned their nation and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue country with neuer dying glories: And in deſpite of Enuy &amp; Obliuion (ſworne enemies to virtue) who would beat downe the memorie of ſuch high ſpirits, by throwing them into baſe and vnknowne graues, Fame does euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more build vp tombs for them in her immortal chronicles.</p>
            <p>Whileſt all men here at home ſate playing with the Sun-beames of Quietnes, and that all the low Country ſtorms began likewiſe to be laid downe calme, ſo that the Engliſh ſouldier had no place to retire to, but to come and lie idlely on the boſome of his own country; behold, a freſh Allarum awakes and calls him from hence into <hi>Sweden.</hi> In the warres of which kingdome what hath bin done lately, I meane only, forſomuch as I, who was a ſeruitor in them, and am now the trumpet to proclaime mine own fortunes there, haue had triall, you ſhall now (déere coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen) receiue afaithfull and honeſt relation.</p>
            <p>Wherein I vow by the honor of a ſouldier, and by the loue, obedience and loyaltie which I owe to no other than my owne natiue countrey, I will ſet downe nothing but that of which (for the moſt part) I haue bin <hi>Oculatus te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis</hi> (an eie-witnes.) And albeit in this relation the truth muſt compell me to deliuer ſuch matter, as happily may terrifie thoſe that neuer bare Armes, nor followed the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of a Souldier, from euer going into <hi>Sweden</hi> and to ſerue in thoſe warres: farre are my thoughts (God beares record of them) from any ſuch diſſwaſion, ſithence all men that know what belongs to the field, can tell, that he who vndertakes the life and condition of a Souldier, muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure worſe and greater miſeries, than I or any Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſent thither can vndergo in <hi>Sweden.</hi> Omitting ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ground of their quarrell, and not ſo much as once
<pb facs="tcp:135785:7"/>touching the fire that hath now ſo ſately kindled warres betwéene the kings of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> becauſe the hearthurnings of kingdomes one againſt an other are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of State, and not fit to be medled with by me, being beyond my cure, I will write a Storie of my owne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes there only, which begins as followeth.</p>
            <p>About a fortnight before Midſomer, which was <hi>1609.</hi> a company of Voluntaries to the number of <hi>1200.</hi> ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, were at ſeueral times ſhipped from <hi>England</hi> to paſſe into <hi>Sweden,</hi> to aide the King of that Countrey in his warres againſt the king of <hi>Poland.</hi> To which aid diuers other nations did likewiſe reſort, as <hi>Frenill, High Dutch, &amp;c</hi> of all whom (as occaſion miniſtreth) mention ſhable made in their due places. Of the Engliſh companies that went thither, the firſt was commaunded by one <hi>Caluine</hi> a Scot; who by appointment was made lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell and chiefe of the other Captaines ouer the footmen. The names of which Captaines are in this following Diſcourſe ſet downe.</p>
            <p>After the firſt company was gone, a ſecond number of <hi>300.</hi> men (of which I the relater of this, was one) were put into one ſhippe belonging to <hi>Swoden,</hi> and came from thence for vs. We being thus aboord, ſailes were preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hoiſted, anchors weighed, and by the aſſiſtance of God, wherewith the dexteritie of the mariners was furthered, in a ſhort time had we gotten into the maine ſea and with a proſperous gale went forward on our voiage. But mans ſecurity oft-times changeth Gods fauors into ſodaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation; for when euery one at the parting from his owne country had a mery and feareleſſe heart to runne to the certaine dangers that ſtood ready to méet him in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forren region: Behold (to put vs all in minde, that God was the God of Hoſtes, and that whether we went foorth to fight, or laied vs downe to ſléepe, whether we were on the ſeas, or on the land, our ſafeties and dangers lay all in his diſpoſing) behold, I ſay, in the height of all
<pb facs="tcp:135785:7"/>our iolity, ſéeing ſo prowd a ſaile ſwelling with the winds to carry vs) the heauens on a ſodaine altered their lookes, ſtorines fell vpon the waters, the waters threatned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to our ſhip, and we that were in her, ſtood wauer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing betwéene the hopes of an vncertaine life, &amp; the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full terrors of a moſt iminent death. In this horror of the ſeas, were we loſſed ſo long, that all our victualles wers almoſt ſpent: the miſery of which, threw vs into more deſperate feares: now were we aſſaulted by double deaths (Famine or Shipwracke) what courſe to take for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe no man preſently knew. Continue without foode it was impoſſible, and as impoſſible was it for vs to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the land in any ſhort time, without the aſſured deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of vs all. At this ſeaſon, our commanders were theſe. <hi>viz</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lieutenant Benſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lieutenant Walton,</hi> who was Prouoſt Martiall of the field.</item>
                  <item>And an Ancient of the Colonels company.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe our Commanders were by our raſhneſſe droue into worſs feares than thoſe were that laid hold vpon our ſelues; for whereas they were reſolued (blow the winds how they could) to continue ſtill at ſea, and not to land, till they ſet footing at their appointed ſhores, the cemmon Souldiers had on the contrary part vowed and reſolued to compell the mariners (ſeeing the preſent miſeries. and no hopes promiſing better) to ſet vs all on ſhore vpon the firſt land that could be diſcouered. Our Commaunders did what they could by diſſwaſion to alter this general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, becauſe they feared it would be the loſſe of the greateſt part of our Companies, if they came once to be ſcattered: and beſides, they knew that it would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to their diſhonour and ſhame, if they ſhould not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the truſt impoſed vpon them by our Captaines, which truſt was to conduct vs &amp; land vs before, whilſt our
<pb facs="tcp:135785:8"/>Chieftaines remained a while behind in <hi>England,</hi> to take vp the reſt of our Companies. Yet all this notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Land being diſcouerd, there was no eloquence in the world able to kéep vs aboord our ſhip, but euery man ſwore if the maſter of the ſhip would not ſet vs on the ſhore, the ſailes ſhould be taken into our own hands, and what was reſolued vpon (touching preſent landing) ſhould in deſpite of danger be effected. Vpon this, the maſter of the ſhip and the mariners told vs, that if we put to land in that place, we ſhould all either periſh for want of victualles, which were not to be had in that country or elſe ſhould haue our throates cut by the people. But the dangers in which we were, and which we felt, being more certaine (as we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined) than any other could be, of which we had yet no ſence or féeling, &amp; our hopes perſwading vs that we could not fall into worſe, than thoſe we taſted already: beſides, all of vs conſtruing the words of the mariners, as not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by them, but as if they had bin ſet on to do ſo by our commanders in the ſhip, who by all means fauored to kéep vs all aboorde: At the laſt we reſolued rather to try our bad fortunes on the land, and to famiſh there (if that kind of death muſt néedes attend vpon vs) than to periſh on the ſeas, which we knew could affoord vs no ſuch mercie as the land was likely to lend vs. So that in the end, we got ſo neare the ſhore ſide, as the ſailes durſt venter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dauger to the ſhip: and there caſting anchor, our ſmall boat was hoiſted out, &amp; on ſhore we went, as faſt as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly we could. When our Officers ſawe, that there was no remedy, nor force to detaine vs aboord, they then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartned vs no longer, but to our great comforts told it, that the maſter of the ſhip (which thing he himſelfe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe openly confeſſed) knew both the Land and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nernour thereof (as indéed we proued afterwards he did:) and therefore deſired they all our companies not to miſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behaue themſelues toward the people, for that it was an Iland called <hi>Iuthland,</hi> vnder the dominion of the king of
<pb facs="tcp:135785:8"/>
               <hi>Denmarke,</hi> but ſubtect to the command of a Lord, who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the king (as his ſubſtitute) was the gouernor.</p>
            <p>And that we might be the better drawne to a ciuill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour towards thinhabitants, our officers further told vs, that they would repaire to the Lord Gouernour of the country, and acquaint him with the cauſe of our vnexpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted landing there; vpon which we all promiſed to offer no violence to the people; neither was that promiſe violated, becauſe we found the inhabitants tractable, and as quiet towards vs, as we to them: yet the greater numbers of them ran away with feare, at the firſt ſight of vs, becauſe (as afterward they reported) it could not be remembred by any of them, that they euer either beheld themſelues, or euer heard any of their anceſtorsreport, that any ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge people had landed in thoſe places and partes of the Iland: for they thought it impoſſible (as they told vs) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> any ſhip ſhould ride ſo néere the ſhore, as ours did, by reaſon of the dangerous Sands.</p>
            <p>Our officers ſo ſoone as they were at land, went to the gouernor of the Iland, whilſt the ſouldiers (who ſtaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them) ran to the houſes of the Ilanders, of purpoſe to talke with the people, and at their hands to buy victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls for a preſent reliefe: but when we came among them, they could neither vnderſtand vs, nor we them; ſo that the market was ſpoiled, and we could get nothing for our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: yet by ſuch ſignes as we could make, they vnderſtood our wants, pittied them, and beſtowed vpon vs (fréely) a little of ſuch things as they had. Yet in the end, a happie means of our reliefe was found out by a ſouldier amongſt vs, who was a <hi>Dane</hi> by birth, but his educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing bin in <hi>Engl.</hi> no man knew him to be other than an engliſhma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Dane</hi> made vſe of his owne natiue language, to the good both of himſelfe, and vs, certifying the people (who the rather beléeued him becauſe he ſpake in their knowne tongue) of the cauſe that compelld vs to land vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their ceaſt, and that we intended no miſchiefe, violence,
<pb facs="tcp:135785:9"/>or mony: to which report of his they giuing credit, ſtood in leſſe feare of vs than before, and thereupon furniſhed vs with all ſuch neceſſaries, as the countrey affoorded to ſuſtaine our wants. The food which we bought of them was only fiſh, and a kind of courſe bread, excéeding cheap. Of which food there was ſuch plentie, that for the value of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. d. we had as much fiſh as xx. men could eate at a meale, and yet none of the worſt ſorts of fiſh, but euen of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beſt and daintieſt, as Mackrels and Lobſters, and ſuch like. In which our trading with the poore ſimple people, we found them ſo ignorant, that many, yea moſt of them regarded not whether you gaue them a counter, or a ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; for the bigger the péece was, the more fiſh they would giue for it: but beſides fiſh wée could get no other ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from them, or at leaſt, could not vnderſtand that they had any other. But obſerue what happened in the meane time that we were thus in trafficke with the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers for victualls, our Officers as before is ſaid) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gone to the lord Gouernor, who lay about xij. engliſh miles from the ſea ſide, the maiſter of our ſhip on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den hoiſed vp ſailes, and away he went, leauing one of his owne men at ſhore, who accompanied our Officers as their guide, through the Iland. The cauſe of the ſhips departure, did ſo much the more amaze vs, by reaſon it was ſo vnexpected, &amp; the reaſon thereof vnknowne to vs: But we imagind the maſter of the ſhip and mariners fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to receiue vs into the veſſel again, becauſe ſome of our men at their being at ſea, threatned the ſailers, and offred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abuſes before they could be brought to ſet vs on land.</p>
            <p>On the next day following the Lord Gouernor of the Iland came to vs, bringing our Officers along with him, yet not being ſo confident of vs, but that (for auoiding of any dangers that might happen) he came ſtrongly guarded with a troope of Horſemen well armed. And (vpon his firſt approach) demaunding where our Ship was, it was folde him in what ſtrange manner it ſtole away and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke
<pb facs="tcp:135785:9"/>vs: he then aſked what wée intended to doe, to which wée all anſwered that we would bée ruled by our Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers: hereupon hee inquired of them what they would haue him to doe in their behalfes, they requeſted nothing elſe at his handes, but onely his fauorable Paſſe through the Country, and a Ship to cary vs forward into <hi>Sweden:</hi> to which requeſt hée made anſwer, that he could grant no ſuch licence vntil he had made the king of <hi>Denmarke</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with our being there, for the Iland belongd to the King he ſayd, and he was no more but an Officer or Subſtitute vnder him. Yet in conſideration that our Ship had ſo left vs in a ſtrange land, hée promiſed to do all that lay in his power to effect our good: but withal told vs that the people had inward feares and were poſſeſſ with ſuſpitions, that our intents of landing vpon ſuch a coaſt (were not as wée our ſelues affirmed, onely to get foode, but rather to make ſpoyle of the poore inhabitants. And therefore to remoue all ſuch feares and Ieloſies out of the peoples hearts, he held it moſt conuenient for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſafeties of both parties, to ſeperat our numbers, and to ſpread vs abroad in the Country, one and one in a houſe, where it was agréede that we ſhould receiue both a lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and meate, and drinke, vntill he had ſent to the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> ſome of his owne men with our Officers, to vnderſtand his Maieſties pleaſure and what ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of vs.</p>
            <p>To this we all agréed, and accordingly for that purpoſe, were by the Lord Gouernor, ſafely by this Armed horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men which were his guard, conducted to his owne houſe. To that place were all the people of the Iland ſummond together, they came at the appointed day to the number of fiue or ſixe hundred, circling vs rownd with Bills Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berds two-hand ſwords and diuers other weapous: And at the firſt ſight of vs grew into ſuch rage, that preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they would haue cutt all our throates, and hewed vs to pieces but that the Authority, of the gouernor kept them
<pb facs="tcp:135785:10"/>from offring violence, yet was he fayne ſo vſe the fayreſt meanes of perſwation to allay their fury. For they would not belieue but that our ariuall there was to deſtroy them, their wiues and children and make a conqueſt at laſt of their Iland, Yet the Gouernor ſhewed vnto them all our number, which was but <hi>300.</hi> men, and thoſe all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weaponed, and ſo conſequently, neither likely, nor able to vndertake any miſchieſe againſt them.</p>
            <p>Then ſtoode vp ſome bolder than the reſt, and teaching the reſt to be more cruell by ſwearing to haue our blouds ere they ſtirred from thence, becauſe (as they alleadged) our yéelding to be diſarmed, was done but in policy to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile them, with ſecureneſſe, whereas they rather doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that ſome ſecond ſupplies were not farre behinde vs, that would likewiſe land on their coaſts, and ioyne in the ſame conqueſt. But the Gouernor looking vpon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of men ſo miſerable as we appeared, with an ete of clearer iudgement and pitty, than the common people could, who were euen blinded with their owne fury, inſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and madneſſe, ſhewed the true nature of a wiſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, by mingling threats with milde ſpeaches, charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vnruely multitude, vpon paine of death, not to touch the leaſt fluger of vs, but to diuide vs equally into ſeuerall villages, as it thould ſéeme beſt vnto them, and to beſtow kind and louing entertainment vpon vs til they heard farder from him, which command of his they accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly performed.</p>
            <p>Inimediatly vpon this ſetling of them and vs in quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, one of our officers with two of the Gouernors men, were ſent away to the king of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> to vnderſtand his Highneſſe pleaſure, which Menengers were no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner diſpatched about the buſines, but the Ilanders grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more and more ſuſpitious, came againe to the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and neuer would ceaſe or giue ouer troubling him, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they had gotten him to make proclamation (in hearing of vs all) That if any of vs would fréely diſcouer the true
<pb facs="tcp:135785:10"/>cauſe of our landing vpon that coaſt, and reueale the plots of any daungerous enterpriſe intended againſt them, he ſhould not onely be rewarded with great ſtore of money, and haue new apparell to his backe, but alſo ſhould with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tortures, impriſonment, or death be ſet frée, and ſent backe againe into his owns countrey This proclamation ſtrucke vs all with feare and aſtoniſhment. becauſe albeit we to our ſelues were not guiltie of any plot, or villanie intended to the place or people, yet we knew this might be a meanes to endanger all our liues, how innocent ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Our ſuſpition of daunger fell out according to our feares, for one <hi>Thomas Griffyn</hi> a Welch man, one of our owne company, but a perſon as it appeared, of a baſe and diuelliſh condition, being tempted with the baite of gold, reſolued to enrich himſelfe, albeit it were by the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of innocent bloud: And thereupon like a falſe traitor to all the reſt of his fellowes, he went and knéeled before the Gouernor, and with a face counterfeiting a guiltines and fearefull deſtruction, told him, that if he might be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen for his part, and haue his life warranted, he would diſcouer ſuch a ſecret, that the opening of the ſame ſhould be good to all the Country, and the concealing thereof the Ilands vtter ruine, with the confuſion of the people. The Gouernor being glad of this diſcouery ſo promiſed, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Griffyn</hi> both of his life, and of the reward, willing him not to feare any danger, but boldly, and with a conſtant boſome to lay open what he knew: vpon which wordes, the traiterous <hi>Iudas</hi> told him for certaine, that we came thither onely and for no other purpoſe than to ſurpriſe the Iland, kill the inhabitants, make ſpoile of their wiues and goodes and hauing ſet fire of their townes and villages to flie to ſea againe. Yet for all this would not the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor beléeue him, celling him it was a matter very vnlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſo ſmall a number, ſo diſtreſſed for want of food, ſo weather-heaten and ſo diſarmed, ſhould venture vpon an enterpriſe ſo full of dangerous euents, but the villaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied,
<pb facs="tcp:135785:11"/>that all theſe complaints of want, were but ſongs to beguile the people, for that vpon the leaſt Allarum gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, other ſhippes that lay houering at ſea, and furniſhed both with men and armor, would on the ſodaine, and that very ſhortly land for the ſame deſire of ſpoile, as theſe their fellows had done, and therefore councelled the Gouernor to preuent ſuch imminent miſchiefes betimes.</p>
            <p>The Gouernour being thus farre vrged, preſently cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before him lieutenant <hi>Walton,</hi> whoſe lodging was appointed in his houſe, and hauing related to him all that <hi>Griffin</hi> had diſcouered, and withall, demaunding of lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant <hi>Walton</hi> what he could ſay to this matter of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and conſpiracy: the lieutenant at the firſt ſtood ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and vtterly denied any ſuch intended villany, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting by the faith of a Souldier, that this report of the Welch man procéeded fom the rancour of a vile traitors heart, and therefore on his knées intreated the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, not to giue credite to ſo baſe a villaine (who for the gréedineſſe of alittle money, went about to ſell all their liues) and to make all thinhabitants of the Iland become murderers:) adding further, that if the Gouernor would but giue him leaue, he would make the treacherous ſlaue before his face there preſently confeſſe that he had belyed his fellowes, and that there was no ſuch Conſpiracie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. The Gouernor gaue him authority to vſe his beſt meanes to trie a traytor, becauſe it was not he ſaid, his deſire to haue the bloud of any Chriſtians, ſhead wrongfully: but if he ſhould find the Welch mans words to be true, he could do no otherwiſe than apprehend vs as traitors to his King and the Country and to lay ſuch pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment vpon vs, as ſhould be ſound due by their lawes. But lieutenant <hi>Walton</hi> earneſtly intreating the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, that if he had any ſuch ill thought of vs, he would be pleaſed to hold him in ſetters as priſoner for vs all, till the trueth might be found out: And that traiterous vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine <hi>Thomas Griffyn</hi> being oppoſed face to face with the
<pb facs="tcp:135785:11"/>lieutenant ſtill continuing in his firſt reſolution, and moſt boldely perſeuering in his accuſations againſt his poore countrymen that lay ſcattred in ſeuerall houſes about the Iland, not hearing of any ſuch matters: Behold how all that <hi>Griffyn</hi> had diſcouered, were by a ſtrange accident ſtrongly confirmed to paſſe for currant, and whatſoeuer lieutenant <hi>Walton</hi> had vttered in oppoſition of <hi>Griffyns</hi> ſlaunders, were held as vntruths, and traps to betray the Country. For, iuſt as the traitor had told the Gouernor, that more ſhips were not farre off, but were ready to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond vs vpon our arriuall, it chanced that in the very heat of this buſineſſe, and their feares of daunger where none was, two other ſhips full of armed ſouldiers came to the ſame place of the Iland where our ſhip put in: Theſe two ſhips had brought ſouldiers out of the lowe Countries (a ceſſation of warres being there) and were going into <hi>Swethland,</hi> as we were, but by croſſe windes and fowle weather, lay ſo long at ſea, that wanting victualls, they were driuen in hither for ſuccour. Whoſe ſodaine approch and ariuall being ſignified to the L. Gouernor, the welch mans words were then thought true; all the fland was preſently vp in Armes to reſiſt the ſtrength and fucie of a moſt dangerous ſuppoſed enemy: and ſo ſecretly did the Inhabitants put on Annes that we who were kept like priſoners amongſt them knew nothing of theſe vproares. But night approaching, the Generall gaue ſpeciall charge that ſecret watch ſhould be ſet and kept ouer euery ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier that lodged in any mans houſe which by the common people was as narrowly performed, for they did not only watch vs as the Gouernor commaunded, but amongſt themſelues a ſecret Conſpiracie was made, that in the dead of night, when we ſhould be faſt aſleepe they ſhould come and take vs in our beds, and there to binde vs with cords: it being an eaſie thing to do ſo, when our company were diuided one from another ouer the whole Iland. At the houre agréed vpon, the plot was put in force, for they
<pb facs="tcp:135785:12"/>entred our Chambers, and bound euerie Souldier as he lay, making them all ready like ſo many ſhéepe, marked out for the ſlaughter. For mine owne part, I had fiue men and thrée women to binde me, who ſo cunningly ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me faſt with cordes, whilſt I ſlept, and felt nothing, nor dreamt of any ſuch matter, that with a twitch onely I was plucked ſtarke naked out of my bed, and laide vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the colde earth vnderneath a Table, with my armes bound behinde me, ſo extreamely hard, as foure men could drawe them together, my féete tied to the foote of the Table, and my necke bound to the vpper part or boord of the Table.</p>
            <p>In theſe miſerable tortures lay I, and all the reſt (in ſeuerall houſes) all that night, and the moſt part of the next day, our armes and legges being pinched and wrung together in ſuch pittileſſe manner, that the verie bloud guſhed out at the ſingers ends of many.</p>
            <p>The enduring of which torments was ſo much the more grieuons, becauſe none knew what we had done that could incenſe them to this ſo ſtrange and ſpitefull cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, neither could we, albeit we inquired, learne of our tormentors the cauſe, becauſe we vnderſtoode not their language. But to me whilſt I ſtood thus vpon the racke, the old woman mine Hoſteſſe came often running in and cryed in her language to me <hi>Traue vp Ieſus,</hi> which was as much to ſay, Pray to Ieſus: by which wordes of her I perceiued they meant to kill me: And ſtill ſhe mumbled out a ſtorie, which I could not interpret, of one <hi>William,</hi> who lay at the next houſe I knew, ſo that I gueſſed her meaning was, that <hi>William,</hi> and all the reſt of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany were in fetters too, like my ſelfe. Yet my priuate thoughts fréed all the reſt, becauſe I was perſwaded they had doue nothing to deſerue ſuch tyrannous handling: Mary of my ſelfe, and my neighbour <hi>William</hi> I ſtoode ſomewhat in a perillous doubt, that they puniſhed vs for a knauerie committed the very ſelfe ſame euening, after
<pb facs="tcp:135785:12"/>which we were intangled in the net, and could by no ſtrugling get out. And that was this</p>
            <p>I happened that night, when this coniuring was to binde vs like wicked ſpirites in ſuch damnable circles, to ſuppe with the ſaid <hi>William</hi> at his lodging: and whileſt we ſate merrily at our meate, not miſtruſting what Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were weauing ouer our heades, to catch vs like flies in their cob-webs, and then to kill vs, into our rowme comes ſtumbling a pedlar, with a packe and a boxe at his backe: We hauing ſo fit an Anuile to breake ieaſts vpon, forgot our ſelues where we were, and brganne to growe merry in Engliſh with Seignior Mountebanke our Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, but he gabling in his language to vs, as faſt as we did in ours to him, both laughed at one another, yet knew not for what. At laſt downe throws he his packe and box on the Table, and being a merry lad, and a cuſtomer to the houſe, went out of our rowme to viſite the houſhold. In the meane time my pew fellow <hi>William</hi> ſpying his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity. opened the Pedlars box, which he thought had bin crammed with ſwéete meates, but in ſtead of Sugar plummes he ſonnd nothing there but Sope, the purchaſe of which ſcowring booty, make <hi>Williams</hi> heart leape for ioy, for (quoth he) my linnen thou ſéeſt is fowle, and this Sope ſhall make me to morrow a cleane gentleman. And thereupon like a conſcionable Chaundler tooke out ſome halfe a pound and gaue great weight: the one halfe of which prize I ſhared in, becauſe I had as much néede as he to be waſhed, yet none of vs both had néede of the ſhauing which we mette withall an one afterwards. But note how iuſtly I was plagued: The ſelfe ſame Peolar was one of the men that helped to binde me; the knaue was leſſe mercifull in tying his knottes than a Beadle or Hang-man, and more nimble to bind my hands behind me, than to binde vp his packe. I ſeeing what ware the Pedlar made of my body, and how villainouſly the reſt of his Conſort played vpon theſe hempen ſtrings, that
<pb facs="tcp:135785:13"/>were wownd vp about my armes, legges, and necke, thought verily that he and his crew had found me guilty for his Sope, and ſo conuemning me behinde my backe, came likewiſe to puniſh me both behind my backe, and to my face.</p>
            <p>But crying out to them, becauſe I ſaw they ieaſted not with me, that the Soape was in my pecket, all the pittifull ſignes I could deuiſe were made, to ſhew I had thruſt it there, but they for all the noiſe I made, plyed their truſſing me vp in halters worſe than fiue hangings, neither regarding the cries of the poore, imitating therein many worldly rich men, nor vnderſtanding whether I curſed them to the pit of Well, for ſo hard binding me, or whether I prayed them to vnlooſe me, neither did Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Pedlar miſſe his halfe pound of Sope, ſo that I was worried by a ſort of curres, I knew how, and where, but I knew not why.</p>
            <p>Whileſt thus the whole Iland was full of the cries of wretched men, and that euery houſe ſéemed a ſhambles, ready to haue Innocents there butchered the next day, and that euery Ilander had the office of a common cutte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throate or executioner, Gods wonderfull working tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ſtreame of all their cruelty: For the two ſhippes that came out of the Lowe Countries, and whoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuall draue ſo many miſerable ſoules almoſt vpon the rockes of deſtruction, hauing in that dolefull and ruinous night, gotten ſome prouiſion aboord, weighed Anchor, and departed towards <hi>Swethland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which happy News béeing ſerued vp at breakefnſt to the Lord Gouernour betimes in the morning, and that the Shippes had offerd no violence to the Country, but had payd for what they tooke: About eleauen of the clocke the very ſame day at noone, wée were all like vnto ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dead men cutt downe, and bidden to ſtand vpon our legges, although very few had ſcarce legges that could ſtand.</p>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <p>This bloudy feaſt being thus ended, and all ſtormes as we well hoped, being now blowne ouer to our frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſitting at liberty from our tormentors; on the necke of theſe former miſeries fell a miſchiefe more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to vs then all the reſt: for tidings were brought to the Gouernour, that our Ancient, who trauailed with the Gouernours two men to the King, had traiterouſly murdered thoſe his guides, and then ran away himſelfe: vpon this rumor, nothing but thundring and lightening flew from the common peoples mouthes: there was no way now with vs but one, and that one was, to haue all our throats cut, or our heads cleft with their axes. But the gouernour pittying our miſfortunes, laboured both by his authority, and by faire ſpéeches, to kéepe that many-headed dogge (the multitude) from barking. And in the end, when he ſaw nothing but the bloud of vs poore Engiſhmen would ſatiſfie their thirſt, becauſe they ſtill held vs in ſuſpition and feare, he moſt nobly, and like a vertuous Magiſtrate, pawned to the inhumane Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals, (to my knowledge) his honour, all that euer he was worth, yea his very life vnto them, that within thrée dayes the meſſengers ſent to the King, ſhould returne home, and that during thoſe thrée dayes we ſhould bée of good behauiour to the Iſlanders: and beſides that
<pb facs="tcp:135785:15"/>they did not returne in ſuch a time, that then he would deliuer vs vp into their hands, to be vſed (or rather miſſe-vſed) in what manner they beſt deſired.</p>
            <p>But God (whoſe helpe is moſt ready, when wretched man hath moſt need of him) put foorth a hand of mercy, and preſerued vs: for our Ancient with the Gouernors two men, came home vpon the third day, to the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours houſe, and brought from the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> his licence, to carry vs not onely through the country, but commanding that we ſhould be allowed ſhipping alſo, at connenient place, to carry vs to <hi>Sweueland,</hi> whither we were to go: And according to this lycence the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour cauſed vs to be called all together the very next day; at which time, <hi>Thomas Griffin</hi> the Welſh <hi>Iudas,</hi> who had all this while lyen feaſting in the houſe of the Lord Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, began to tremble and to repent him of his villan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, begging moſt baſe forgiueneſſe on his knées, both from the Gouernour, and vs his countrimen and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Souldiers, proteſting that what he did came out of his feare to ſaue his owne life. But our Officers (vpon hearing him ſpeake thus) had much adoe to kéepe the companies from pulling downe the houſe whore <hi>Griffin</hi> lay, becauſe they would in that rage haue hewed the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine in péeces.</p>
            <p>But leauing him and all ſuch betrayers of mens bloud to the hell of their owne conſciences, let vs ſet forward out of this infortunate Iland, &amp; not ſtay in any place elſe, till in ſmall boates we come by water to <hi>Elzinore</hi> in <hi>Denmarke,</hi> where wee ioyfully got aboard once more; and are hoyſing vp ſailes for <hi>Sweueland.</hi> Yet euen in this ſun-ſhine day a ſtorme falles vpon vs too: for our Officers not hauing ſufficient money to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs with victuals, we were enforced to pawne our Ancient and Lieftenant <hi>Walton,</hi> for the ſafe returne of the ſhip, with condition that they ſhould not be releaſed vntill a ſufficient ſumme of money was ſent to defray all
<pb facs="tcp:135785:15"/>charges. So that we left our Officers behinde vs; but the King of <hi>Sweueland</hi> did afterwards releaſe them, and then they came to vs. But before their comming, we hauing a good winde, landed at a place called <hi>Newleas</hi> in <hi>Sweue:</hi> and from thence were carryed to <hi>Stockholme,</hi> (the Kings ſeate) and there was the King at the ſame time: betwéene which two places it was a dayes march on horſebacke.</p>
            <p>Vpon this our arriuall at <hi>Stockholme,</hi> we met with the reſt that had gone before vs, and with diuers others of our countrymen, that came out of the <hi>Low-countries,</hi> as before is related. In this place we lay ſo long, and had ſuch poore meanes, that wanting money to buy ſoode, we wanted foode to maintaine life, and ſo a number of vs were ready to ſterue: till in the end, our miſeries ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vs deſperate, we fell together by the eares with the <hi>Burgers</hi> of the towne: in which ſcambling confuſion and mutiny, euery man got one thing or other, of which he made preſent money to relieue his body withall: yet lay we at the walles of the citty, crying out continually for money, money, till our throates grew hoarſe with bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but the ſtones of the walles gaue more comfort to vs, then the inhabitants. One day (aboue all the reſt) we heard, that the King was to ride a hunting; and wée imagining that all the abuſes, wrongs, and miſeries, which we endured, procéeded from ſome vnder-hand hard dealing, and packing of our Captaines and Officers, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to gather about the King at his comming forth, &amp; to cry out for mony: but the King being angry (as we ſuppoſed) came riding amongſt vs, drawing his piſtoll from the ſaddle bow, as if he purpoſed to haue ſhot ſome of vs: but ſeeing none of vs to ſhrinke from him, nor to be diſmaied, he rode backe againe, we following him, &amp; deſiring; he would either giue vs money, or elſe to kill vs out-right; one amongſt the reſt (whoſe name was <hi>William Attane</hi>) ſpake to the King aloud, thus: <hi>I hold it
<pb facs="tcp:135785:16"/>honor to dye by the hands of a King, but baſely to ſterue to death, I will neuer ſuffer it.</hi> Vpon theſe our clamors, the King looking better vpon our neceſſities, ſent money the next day, and immediatly after gaue vs a moneths meanes in mony, and two mone ths meanes in cloath, to make vs apparrell.</p>
            <p>Of the cloath we receiued ſome part, but the money being paid, was by our Captaines ſent into England, to their wiues; no part of it euer comning to the poore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldiers hands: for preſently vpon this, we were commanded aboord the ſhips, with promiſe that when we were aboord we ſhould haue our money. But being in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhips vnder hatches, away were we carryed with proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion onely of one moneths victuals, when by reaſon of the weather we were forced to lye eight wéekes at ſea: in all which time we had nothing but pickelled herrings, and ſalt ſtremlings, with ſome ſmall quantity of hard dryed meates: by which ill dyet, many of our men fell ſicke and dyed. In the ſhip wherein I was, wée liued fouretéene dayes without bread, all our beſt foode being ſalt herrings, which we were glad to eate raw; the beſt of vs all hauing no better ſuſtenance.</p>
            <p>At the laſt it pleaſed God to ſend vs to a place called <hi>Vfraſound</hi> in <hi>Fynland,</hi> where we landed, (<hi>Fynland</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubiect to the King of <hi>Sweueland.</hi>) From <hi>Vfraſound</hi> we were to goe to <hi>Weyborough,</hi> a chiefe towne in the country of <hi>Fynland:</hi> where we no ſooner arrriued, but our Souldiers ran ſome one way, and ſome another, ſo long that the Captaines were left alone with the ſhips. This running away of them, being done onely to ſéeke foode, ſo great was their hunger.</p>
            <p>By this careleſſe diſperſing themſelues, they loſt the command of the whole country, which they might eaſily haue had, if they had bene vnited together: and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were depriued of that benefite, but of horſes alſo which were allowed by the King for them to ride vpon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135785:16"/>
So that, what by the reaſon of the tedious iourney, (which we were to trauell, being foureſcore leagues) and what by reaſon of the extreme cold, being a moneth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſtmas, at which time the ſnow fell, and neuer went off the ground vntill Whitſontide following, but all the raine and all the the ſnow that fell, fréezing continually, diuers of our men were ſterued to death with the froſt.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Some loſt their fingers, ſome their toes, ſome their noſes, many their liues: inſomuch that when wee all met at <hi>Weyborough,</hi> we could make no make no more but <hi>1400.</hi> able men; and yet when we were landed at
<pb facs="tcp:135785:17"/>
               <hi>Vfraſound</hi> we were <hi>2000.</hi> ſtrong, the extremity of the cold country hauing killed ſo many of our Souldiers in ſo little time.</p>
            <p>At our landing at <hi>Weyborough</hi> we had good hopes to receiue better comforts, both of money and victuals: for the inhabitants told vs, the King had allowed it vs, and in that report they ſpake truth: yet contrary to our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, we lay there about <hi>14.</hi> dayes, and had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a little Rice, of which we made bread, and a little butter, which was our beſt reliefe. Drinke had we none, nor money: our Captaines gaue vs certaine le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne pelches onely made of ſhéeps ſkinnes, to kéepe vs from the cold.</p>
            <p>At this place we receiued Armes to defend vs againſt the enemy, and ſixe companies that were allowed by the King for horſemen, receiued horſes there. From thence we were to march into Ruſſia, where our enemies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued. But the iourney was long and vncomfortable: for we marched from Newyeares day vntill Whitſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide, continually in ſnow, hauing no reſt, but onely a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in the nights. So that the miſeries and miſ-fortunes which we endured vpon the borders of <hi>Fynland,</hi> were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt iuſufferable, by reaſon the number of them ſéemed infinite. For all the people had forſaken their houſes long before wee came, becauſe they were euermore op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Souldiers: by which meanes wee could get neither meate nor drinke, but were glad to hunt cats, and to kill them, or any beaſt wee could lay hold on, and this we baked, and made them ſerue for dayly ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>The greateſt calamity of all was, we could get no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to drinke, it had bene ſo long frozen vp, and the ſnow ſo déepe, that it was hard to ſay, whether we marched o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer water, or vpon land. So that we were compelled to digge vp ſnow, and with ſtones red hot, to melt in tubs. and then to drinke it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135785:17"/>
This affliction continued about <hi>12.</hi> or <hi>14.</hi> dayes, till we came into Ruſſia. Vpon our very firſt entrance into which kingdome, we marched ouer an Arme of the Sea, that was <hi>8.</hi> leagues ouer, many of vs ſteruing to death in that paſſage, by the cold fréezing winds that blew the ſame day. In which froſty iourney, I ſaw ſo much bread as a man might buy for twelue pence, ſold away in little bits for the value of forty ſhillings.</p>
            <p>But this miſery ended the next day, at our ſetting foot into Ruſſia, where we found plenty both of corne and cattle; onely the people of the country ran away, leauing all their goods behinde them, but ſo cunningly hidden, that the beſt pollicy of ours could hardly finde them out.</p>
            <p>By this meanes of the peoples running away, wée were glad to play the Millers, and to grinde all our corne our ſelues, to bake our bread, and to dreſſe our owne vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals. Then marched we vp to <hi>Nouegrade,</hi> (a chiefe citty in Ruſſia) where we were to receiue all our meanes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſted behind vnpayed: but our Captains beguiled vs, and kept it for themſelues: yet to ſt op our mouthes, they told vs we ſhould go into <hi>Muſcouy,</hi> and there all recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings ſhould be made euen.</p>
            <p>Wée had ſcarce marched aboue thrée dayes towards <hi>Muſcouy,</hi> but that newes came, how a certaine number of our enemies lay in a ſconce by the way; the ſtrength of them was not perfectly knowne, but it was thought they were not aboue <hi>700.</hi> And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we muſt vſe ſome ſtrat agem to expell them fro thence: vpon which relation, our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains drew forth to the number of <hi>300.</hi> Engliſh horſmen, and <hi>200.</hi> French horſemen: ſo that in all we were about <hi>500.</hi> that were appointed to ſet vpon the ſuppoſed <hi>700.</hi> Polanders (our enemies) that ſo lay inſconced: vpon whom we went. Our chiefe Commander in that ſeruice was <hi>Monſieur La Veile,</hi> a French man, who ſo valiantly led vs on, that the enemy hearing of our comming, fled o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a water that was by the ſeonce; yet not with ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:135785:18"/>ſpéede, but that we ſlew to the number of <hi>400.</hi> of their ſide, and loſt onely thrée men of our owne: but we tooke the ſconce.</p>
            <p>About the ſconce ſtood a faire towne called <hi>Arioua,</hi> with a riuer called the <hi>Volga,</hi> running through the middle, but no bridge ouer it: onely a few boates and ſloates, (made &amp; cut out of trées) were there, to carry the people ouer from the one halfe of the towne to the other.</p>
            <p>This ſconce furmſhed vs not only with great ſtore of riches, but alſo with a number of Poliſh horſes: and as many armes as ſerued to arme <hi>500.</hi> men, our want of that commodity being as much as of any thing beſides: for of thoſe fiue hundred men that went vpon the ſeruice, there were not <hi>300.</hi> fixed armes; yet through the hand of him that deales victories, or ouerthrows, as it pleaſeth hun beſt, the day was ours.</p>
            <p>Ouer this riner <hi>Volga</hi> the enemies were neuer driuen before, either by the Emperour of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> or by the King of <hi>Sweueland:</hi> for which cauſe (as afterward we heard) the next day when they departed from the other ſide of the riuer, they burnt that halfe of the town on which ſide they were themſelues, and in moſt bloudy, barbarous, &amp; cruell manner, made hauock both of men, women, &amp; chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, albeit (not aboue halfe a yeare before, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabitants on that ſide had reuolted from their owne Emperour, &amp; turned to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In which tyrannical vprore, their cuſtome was, to fill a houſe full of people, &amp; then (the doores being locked vpon them, that none might iſſue forth) the houſe was fired about their eares: and oftentimes were yong children taken by the héeles, and caſt into the middeſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlames. This inhumane tyrranny being practiſed not onely, by the Poles, that were our enemies, but euen by thoſe Ruſſes that were traytors to their owne Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, &amp; ſerued vnder the Poles, and were called <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes,</hi> whoſe cruelty farre excéeded the Poliſh.</p>
            <p>The towne being thus burnt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, all the <hi>6000.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:135785:18"/>(which as I ſaid before, fled ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riuer, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſconce, &amp; were by vs ſuppoſed to be but <hi>700.</hi>) came down in full battalion to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riuers ſide with ſuch fierceneſſe, as if pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently they and their horſes would haue ſwom ouer, to fight with vs, which being perceiued, our poore <hi>500.</hi> ſtood ready to reſiſt them. But whether they feared our num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to be greater then they were, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we had ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecret forces, I know not: but away they marched, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelfe ſame day in which they came downe in that brauery not doing any thing; of which we for our parts, were not much ſorry; becauſe if the battailes had ioyned, we knew our ſelues farre vnable to withſtand them. And this was the ſeruice of the moſt note that we went vpon.</p>
            <p>Two or thrée other ſconces &amp; towns we tooke from our enemies, they not once daring to reſiſt vs, becauſe they knew nothing of our numbers &amp; force. But the diſhoneſt dealings of our Captaines, made the whole army diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; inſomuch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> our Souldiers would often times deny to go forth vpon ſeruice, becauſe they had béene almoſt a yeare in the land, and had receiued no more but one <hi>Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> (amounting to the value of <hi>10.</hi> s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Engliſh.) So that vpon theſe diſcontents, <hi>50.</hi> of our men ran away to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy at one time, &amp; diſcouered to them our ſtrength. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which we durſt not be ſo bold as before we had béene.</p>
            <p>The fire of a new conſpiracy was likewiſe kindling, but it was perceiued, and quenched with the bloud of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſpirators, of which the chiefe were hanged. On there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therefore wée went: when wée came within <hi>40.</hi> leagues of <hi>Muſcouy,</hi> newes was brought that the enemy had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaguerd <hi>7000.</hi> Ruſſes that were our friends, and that vnleſſe we forced the ſiege to breake vp, the <hi>7000.</hi> Ruſſes would euery man bee ſterued where they lay. This ſad report, (albeit wée had reſolued neuer to go vpon any more ſeruice, vntill wée had our pay) ſo wrought in our hearts, that we much pittyed the miſeries of others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we our ſelues had taſted of the like.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135785:19"/>
Our Generall (whoſe name was <hi>Euerhorne</hi>) was a Fynlander, and with a company of Fynland blades (as they tearme them,) well appointed on horſebacke, was by the King of <hi>Sweueland,</hi> ſent after vs, as our Conuoy, vntil we ſhould come to <hi>Pontus le Guard,</hi> who was chiefe Generall ouer the whole army of ſtrangers that came into the land: ſo that according as he was ſent and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the King, he ouertooke vs before we came to <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oua.</hi> By the intreaty therefore of this Fynlander, and the flattering promiſes of our owne Captaines, we were contented to go vpon this ſeruice, and to deliuer the Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or to dye our ſelues in the action. Yet with conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that (as they promiſed to vs) wee ſhould by the way, méete our chiefe Generall <hi>(Pontus le Guard)</hi> who with certaine numbers of Engliſh, French, &amp; Dutch, (which the yeare before were come into the land) was vpon a march out of <hi>Muſcouy,</hi> not onely to méete vs, but to ioyne with vs, and pay vs all our money which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned good to vs; prouided likewiſe, that ſo ſoone as euer we ſhould releaſe the <hi>7000.</hi> Ruſſes, our money ſhould be payed downe. On theſe conditions (I ſay) we yéelded to to go vpon the buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>At length <hi>Pontus le Guard</hi> met vs (according to the promiſe:) and with him was money brought to pay vs, and his word giuen that preſently wee ſhould receiue it. But the lamentable eſtate, in which the poore beſieged Ruſſes were (within the ſconce) being at the point of death for want of food, required rather ſpéedy execution, then deliberation: ſo that the neceſſities of their hard for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes crauing haſte, on we went, hauing about <hi>19.</hi> or <hi>20000.</hi> Ruſſes, that were people of the ſame country, ioyned to our army, to aide them in this enterprize. But as we all were vpon a march, the enemy hauing receiued intelligence of our approaching, ſet forward to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>8000.</hi> Lanciers and more, to intercept vs by the way: and being within one dayes march of the place to
<pb facs="tcp:135785:19"/>which we were likewiſe going, they ſet fire vpon thrée or foure villages hard by the place where we lay at gcaſſe with our horſes, for a token that they were comming. And this was done vpon Midſommer day laſt in the morning, by breake of day. Then came they thundring with ſhouts and cryes to ſet vpon vs: but no ſooner was the Alarum giuen, when the greateſt part of thoſe <hi>19.</hi> or <hi>20000.</hi> Ruſſes, that were ioyned to vs as our aide, fled moſt baſely, before any blow was ginen. This ſodaine cowardize of theirs, ſomewhat amazed vs: but the houre being now come, wherein we were not to talke of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, but to go méete dangers, with our ſixe companies of Engliſh horſe, we brauely reſiſted the Holanders, and with great hurt to them, but with little loſſe vpon our part, charged them thrée ſeuerall times.</p>
            <p>At laſt <hi>Pontus le Guard</hi> (our chiefe Generall) tooke his héeles and fled too, leauing vs vtterly deſtitute of all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: which much aſtoniſhed vs, as not well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what to do: for our greateſt ſtrength (being by their flight) taken from vs, none but we ſtrangers were left in the field, and of vs there was not in all, aboue two thouſand, and of that number there were aboue ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred French horſemen, who ſéeing both the Generall gone, and the Ruſſes fled, turned their backes vpon vs, and ran away too moſt valiantly, yet not out of the field, but to the enemy.</p>
            <p>Then were we not aboue twelue or rouretéene hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at the moſt left to reſiſt eight thouſand at the leaſt: vpon whom notwithſtanding, our ſixe companies of Engliſh horſemen, charged thrée ſeuerall times, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great loſſe, but with much honour: And at the fourth time, for want of powers to ſecond them (which the French ſhould haue done) all our ſixe companies were ſcattered and ouerthrowne with the loſſe of few of our colours. The captaines ouer theſe ſixe companies of horſe, were theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135785:20"/>
               <hi>Viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Captaine <hi>Crale,</hi> of whoſe company I was.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Captaine <hi>Kendricke.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Captaine <hi>Benſon.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Captaine <hi>Carre.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Captaine <hi>Colbron.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Captaine <hi>Creyton.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſixe Captaines had not in all their companies, aboue <hi>500.</hi> men.</p>
            <p>In this battaile, Captaine <hi>Creyton</hi> was ſlaine in the field; Captaine <hi>Cràle</hi> was ſhot in the knée, and within a ſhort time after, dyed of that wound; not aboue twelue of his company eſcaping. Captaine <hi>Kendricke</hi> was wounded in diuers places of the head, and dyed. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Benſon</hi> was ſhot in the hand, and wounded in the head, and yet eſcaped, and liued: onely Captaine <hi>Carre</hi> and his Cornet eſcaped, but all his company ſcattered &amp; loſt. Diuers other Officers were ſlaine, whoſe names I cannot remember.</p>
            <p>Thus were all our Engliſh horſemen diſperſed and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne, to the number of <hi>500.</hi> and vpwards: Our Generall <hi>Euerhorne</hi> with his companies of <hi>Fynland,</hi> or <hi>Fynſco</hi> blades, were alſo put to retraite: ſo that there was not left in the field, aboue <hi>6.</hi> or <hi>700.</hi> which were foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. And of theſe, one halfe was Engliſh, one halfe Dutch, who kept onely a certaine place by a wood ſide, barricadoed about with Wagons, hauing with them foure field péeces, with which they did great ſpoyle to the enemy. But their number being but few, neither durſt they venture on the enemy, nor durſt the enemy enter vpon them, but kept them ſtill (as it were beſieged) in that place only, becauſe they could no wayes eſcape. The inconuenience of which cooping vp in ſo narrow a roome, being looked into, and the dangers on euery ſide well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, it was held fitteſt for ſafety, to ſummon the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to a parlée. In which parley, the enemy offered, that if they would yéeld, and fall to their ſides, they ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:135785:20"/>haue good quarter kept. And if any man had deſire to go for his owne country, he ſhould haue liberty to go with a paſport, from the King of Poland. Or if any would ſerue the King of Poland, he ſhould haue the allowance of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good meanes duly paid him. Vpon thieſe compoſitions they all yéelded, and went to the enemy; only Captaine <hi>Yorke</hi> &amp; his Officers, with ſome few of their Souldiers, went backe into the country, and came not to the enemy; as the reſt had done: who from thence marched vp to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Poliſh Leaguer, being ten miles diſtant from the place, and there they continued. But ſuch as deſired to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile to their owne ceuntries, were ſent to the King of of Polands Leaguer, which lay at that time, at a place called <hi>Smolenſco,</hi> and there accordingly had their Paſſe, to the number of <hi>100.</hi> of which number I my ſelfe was one. What became of the reſt, I know not: but I with fiue more, held together in trauaile, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we came to <hi>Dantzicke,</hi> a great towne in Pruſſia, being diſtant from <hi>Smolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſco,</hi> one hundred leagues.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
